avivacommunityfund.org 2018-10-08

# important

Aviva Canada Inc. Privacy Policy
Taking care of what’s important to you
Table of Contents
Introduction
Privacy in Canada
Definition of Personal Information
Privacy Policy: the ten principles
Accountability
Identifying Purposes
Consent
Limiting Collection
Limiting Use, Disclosure, and Retention
Accuracy
Safeguards
Openness
Customer Access
Challenging Compliance
Appendix
How to contact Aviva’s Privacy Officer
Updated June 2017
                                        1

Introduction
Aviva Canada Inc. and our member companies1 (“Aviva”) are committed to protecting and
keeping private our policyholders’ and partners’ personal information. Our Privacy Policy
sets out principles on the collection, protection, use and disclosure of personal information.
All employees are required to comply with the Privacy Policy in the execution of their daily
activities.
Personal Information is collected by Aviva and its representatives for the purposes of:
        communicating with you
        underwriting and pricing your policy application and any subsequent policy
         changes or renewals
        servicing your ongoing insurance needs
        investigating and settling claims
        detecting and preventing fraud
        analyzing business results, compiling statistics, performing administrative tasks
         such as accounting and information system activities and conducting marketing
         and underwriting research and modeling
        reporting to regulatory or industry entities
        providing you with information on our products and services
        training employees and monitoring for quality assurance, and;
        acting as required or authorized by law
At Aviva, we identify to our customers the rationale for collecting the personal information
at or prior to its actual collection. Our consumers in turn must expressly consent to its
collection, or consent may be implied by their actions. It’s our promise to ensure that the
personal information collected on our customers is only used for the purpose for which it
was originally intended.
We take our commitment to protecting personal information seriously. For more
information, please review the content of our Privacy Policy.
Greg Somerville President and Chief Executive Officer
1
  See Appendix for Aviva Canada Inc. member companies
                                                                                            2

Privacy in Canada
Federal Legislation: Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act
The Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA) sets
standards and regulations governing the collection, use and disclosure of personal
information by private sector organizations.
This law impacts the way private corporations, federal agencies, not-for-profit
organizations and associations handle personal information. At the same time, it clearly
establishes a code of practices to ensure that the personal information of Canadians is
handled respectfully and privately.
Provincial Legislation
The province of Quebec was the first jurisdiction in North America to enact comprehensive
personal information protection legislation for the private sector. An Act respecting the
Protection of Personal Information in the Private Sector sets out fair information practices
for businesses operating in Quebec.
The provinces of Alberta and British Columbia enacted their own privacy laws, the
Personal Information Protection Act of British Columbia and the Personal Information
Protection Act of Alberta, on January 1, 2004.
As other provinces enact similar legislation, organizations conducting commercial activity
within a province will be subject to the provisions of their provincial laws rather than
PIPEDA. However, PIPEDA will continue to regulate cross-border, inter-provincial and
international trade and commerce.
Definition of Personal Information
“Personal Information” is defined as information about an identifiable individual, but does
not include the name, title or business address or telephone number of an employee of an
organization. This is a very broad definition and may encompass most types of information
held such as race, medical, criminal, employment and financial history. The legislation
only applies to information collected, used or disclosed in the course of commercial
activities.
The types of Personal Information that we may collect in order to fulfill the Purposes
identified in Principle Two of this Policy include an individual's address, telephone number,
date of birth, family status, marital status, occupation, medical and health records, assets,
liabilities, income, credit rating, credit and payment records, an individual's previous
insurance experience, including claims history, individual's driving record, policy number
and vehicle identity number.
However, Personal Information does not include certain prescribed sources of public
information such as:
                                                                                           3

       Personal Information consisting of the name, address and telephone number of a
        subscriber that appears in a telephone directory that is available to the public,
        where the subscriber can refuse to have the Personal Information appear in the
        directory;
       Personal Information including the name, title, address and telephone number of
        the individual that appears in a professional or business directory, listing or notice,
        that is available to the public, where the collection use and disclosure of the
        Personal Information relates directly to the purpose for which the information
        appears in the directory, listing or notice;
       Personal Information that appears in a registry collected under statutory authority
        and to which a right of public access is authorized by law, where the collection,
        use and disclosure of the Personal Information relate directly to the purpose for
        which the information appears in the registry;
       Personal Information that appears in a record or document of a judicial or quasi-
        judicial body, that is available to the public, where the collection and disclosure of
        the Personal Information relates directly to the purpose for which the information
        appears in the record or document; and
       Personal Information that appears in a publication, including a magazine, book or
        newspaper, in printed or electronic form, that is available to the public, where the
        individual has provided the information.
Aviva’s Privacy Policy: the ten principles
The objective of our Privacy Policy is to ensure the protection of Aviva customers’ Personal
Information. This includes Personal Information residing within Aviva and Personal
Information provided to other third parties in the conduct of commercial activities. To attain
this goal, Aviva complies with the following principles:
       Aviva is responsible for Personal Information under its possession, custody, or
        control and a designated Privacy Officer is accountable for Aviva's compliance to
        the Privacy Policy and Procedures. [Principle One]
       Aviva shall inform individuals of the purposes for which Personal Information is
        collected at or before the time the information is collected. [Principle Two]
       Aviva requires the knowledge and consent of the individual for the collection, use,
        or disclosure of Personal Information, except in certain circumstances where
        consent is not required. [Principle Three]
       Aviva shall only collect Personal Information that is necessary for the identified
        purposes and such information shall be collected by fair and lawful means.
        [Principle Four]
       Aviva shall not use or disclose Personal Information for purposes other than those
        for which it was collected, except with the consent of the individual or as required
                                                                                             4

         or permitted by law. Aviva shall only retain Personal Information as long as
         necessary for the fulfillment of such purposes. [Principle Five]
        Aviva shall ensure that Personal Information is as accurate, complete, and up-to-
         date as is deemed necessary for the purposes for which it is to be used.
         [Principle Six]
        Aviva shall protect Personal Information by establishing and operating security
         safeguards appropriate to the sensitivity of the information, which is held, and to
         prevent any unauthorized activity relative to the information. [Principle Seven]
        Aviva shall make available to individuals upon receipt of a written request, specific
         information about its policies and practices relating to the management of Personal
         Information and its complaints handling process. [Principle Eight]
        Aviva shall, upon the receipt of a written request from individuals, inform them of
         the existence, use, and disclosure of any Personal Information about them, and
         they shall be given access to such information except as may be limited by law.
         Aviva shall amend Personal Information as deemed appropriate to ensure
         continued accuracy. [Principle Nine]
        Aviva shall provide a means for individuals to challenge compliance with
         the above with Aviva’s Privacy Officer. [Principle Ten].
PRINCIPLE ONE: Accountability
Aviva is responsible for Personal Information under its possession, custody or
control and a designated Privacy Officer is accountable for Aviva’s compliance to
the Privacy Policy and Procedures.
We are responsible for all Personal Information under our control, whether supplied to us
directly by you or by a third party, or that we have provided to a third party for processing.
We have established policies and procedures to comply with our Privacy Policy, and have
designated a Privacy Officer who is responsible for ensuring we comply with privacy
legislation.
Please click here to contact our Privacy Officer regarding your specific privacy questions
or concerns.
PRINCIPLE TWO: Identifying Purposes
Aviva shall inform individuals of the purposes for which Personal Information is
collected at or before the time the information is collected.
                                                                                            5

Aviva shall collect your Personal Information from, but not limited to, government
agencies, brokers, agents, insurers, other insurance reporting or data sharing agencies,
credit bureaus and directly from you to:
       Communicate with you
       Underwrite and price your policy application and any subsequent policy changes
        or renewals
       Service your ongoing insurance needs
       Investigate and settle claims
       Detect and prevent fraud
       Analyze business results, compile statistics, perform administrative tasks such as
        accounting and information system activities and conduct marketing and
        underwriting research and modeling
       Report to regulatory or industry entities
       Provide you with information on our products and services
       Train employees and monitor for quality assurance
       Act as required or as authorized by law
If we require your Personal Information for any purpose other than as identified above,
Aviva will seek your consent prior to using it.
Where permitted by law, your consent may be obtained to collect and use your credit
information for the purposes of offering you a discount on our products.
PRINCIPLE THREE: Consent
Aviva requires the knowledge and consent of the individuals for the collection, use,
or disclosure of their Personal Information, except in certain circumstances where
consent is not required.
General
We issue an insurance policy with the understanding that, in addition to providing your
consent, you have obtained the consent from all persons named in your insurance policy
for the collection, use and disclosure of their Personal Information, for the purposes
outlined above.
Obtaining Consent
You can provide consent to the collection, use and disclosure of your Personal Information
expressly or consent may be implied by your actions.
Express consent can be given orally or in writing. It is given by agreement or action on
the part of the customer, to acquire or accept a product or service. For example, express
oral consent can be given over the telephone, or express written consent can be given by
signing an application form or an agreement which may relate to Personal Information.
                                                                                         6

Express consent by an action can be given by clicking an accept button on a computer
screen. If oral express consent is given, Aviva and/or intermediaries will document and/or
record the conversation, specifically the name, date, and details of the conversation in
either hard or soft copy within the appropriate policy or claim file documentation in order
that it may be easily located and accessed should this be necessary.
Consent will also be given by you and accepted by us when you are provided our privacy
notice along with your policy and you do not advise that you wish to opt out of all or portions
of it.
Implied consent can be inferred from the relationship between the parties or from the
nature of the dealings between the parties. For example, when you give Personal
Information to an insurance broker or agent for the purpose of obtaining insurance, it is
reasonable to infer that there is implied consent to the disclosure of that information to the
insurer to meet your insurance needs.
When your Personal Information is highly sensitive, for example medical reports or
financial records such as income tax returns, we obtain your express written consent
before using it.
In addition when you make changes to your policy or when your policy automatically
renews, you are agreeing that any consent you have previously provided to us relative to
your policy remains in effect unless the consent is otherwise withdrawn.
Who Can Give Consent
Consent may be given by the individual or by an authorized representative (such as a
person having power of attorney, or a legal guardian). Aviva will verify authorization by
requesting identification of the representative, the reason for representation, and if
applicable, the approval of representation by the applicable individual.
                                                                                              7

When consent is not required:
Knowledge and consent are not required in many circumstances under the law for the
collection, use and disclosure of Personal Information, such as:
       Where it would compromise the availability or accuracy of the Personal Information
        relating to the breach of an agreement or the contravention of any law, including
        the detection and prevention of fraud;
       For compliance with subpoenas, search warrants, and other court or government
        orders;
       When Personal Information is transferred to lawyers retained by Aviva pursuant to
        the contractual obligation in the insurance policy to defend legal actions against
        the insured;
       When, under exceptional circumstances, Aviva may, under a public requirement,
        disclose Personal Information to appropriate authorities in matters of significant
        public interest;
       Where the individual is a minor, seriously ill, or mentally incapacitated, and seeking
        consent is impossible or inappropriate;
       Where the Personal Information is publicly available and is specified by the
        regulations; and
       When required by law.
Withdrawing your consent:
Subject to certain legal and contractual restrictions and reasonable notice, you may refuse
or withdraw consent to the collection, use or disclosure of Personal Information at any time
by notifying our Privacy Officer in writing. In addition, you may also opt out of certain
communications we may send you regarding other products and services. However, you
should be aware that withdrawing your consent may affect our ability to respond to your
insurance needs.
PRINCIPLE FOUR: Limiting Collection
Aviva shall only collect Personal Information that is necessary for the Identified
Purposes mentioned above and such information shall be collected by fair and
lawful means.
We only collect information that we require to do business with you. We will collect it
openly, fairly and lawfully.
PRINCIPLE FIVE: Limiting use, disclosure and
retention
Aviva shall not use or disclose Personal Information for purposes other than those
for which it was collected, except with the consent of the individual or as required
or permitted by law. Aviva shall only retain Personal Information as long as
necessary for the fulfillment of such purposes.
                                                                                             8

General
There are situations specific to the Property and Casualty insurance business where we
will use, disclose and retain Personal Information as dictated by prudent insurance
practices. Examples of these situations include:
       Risk sharing: transfer of Personal Information to other insurers and/or to
        reinsurers;
       Information services: disclosure for underwriting, claims, classification and rating
        purposes;
       Insurance services: disclosures to providers of goods and services to Aviva such
        as insurance reporting or data sharing agencies, loss control managers, and
        claims adjusters; and
       Insurance intermediaries: brokers and agents.
We do not use or disclose your Personal Information for purposes not identified in Principle
Two unless we have your consent or it is required by law. We will keep your information
only for as long as it is needed.
Disclosure within Aviva
Aviva Canada Inc. and/or its member companies may internally share your personal
information for the purposes identified in this policy with its Canadian affiliates or other
related companies outside of Canada. Only such companies with legitimate business
reasons will have access to your Personal Information and must ensure that Personal
Information in their possession is securely held.
Disclosure to Third Parties
We may disclose your Personal Information to: third parties, which include brokers,
agents, private investigators, and adjusters. Third parties are also subject to PIPEDA and
other applicable privacy legislation. Only those companies or individuals who are
authorized, based on their need to carry out work for the purposes identified in Principle
Two, can have Personal Information disclosed to them.
Furthermore, should Aviva Canada Inc. and/or any of its member companies become
involved in any business transaction including purchase or sale, merger or amalgamation
or a financing arrangement, pertaining to any of its business assets, your Personal
Information may need to be shared with applicable third parties to complete such a
transaction.
Disclosure Outside of Canada
Aviva Canada Inc. and/or any of its member companies may use service providers located
outside of Canada or related companies located outside of Canada to collect, use,
disclose or store your Personal Information. Only those companies or individuals, who
are authorized, based on their need to carry out work for the purposes identified in
Principle Two, can perform such functions.
                                                                                           9

Where your Personal Information is collected, used, disclosed or stored outside of
Canada, we will attempt to contractually protect it, however, it may be subject to the laws
of that jurisdiction and may be accessed by the courts, law enforcement and national
security services of that jurisdiction.
The jurisdictions where Personal Information may be collected, used, disclosed and stored
include the European Union and the United States of America. To obtain further
information on Aviva’s policies and practices with respect to service providers outside of
Canada you may contact the Aviva Privacy Officer.
Retention Periods
The retention periods for Personal Information are consistent with Aviva’s Record
Retention Policy and Schedule, which in turn meets provincial and federal legislation
requirements.
Your Personal Information will only be retained for as long as necessary for Aviva to serve
you or as long as may be required for legal purposes. As soon as any of the Personal
Information reaches its maximum retention period, it is either destroyed, made
anonymous, or archived from operating systems to a secured, limited access site.
Personal Information that still serves an identified purpose may be retained indefinitely
provided that it is archived outside of the regular operating environment with more
restrictive accessibility.
PRINCIPLE SIX: Accuracy
Aviva shall ensure that Personal Information is as accurate, complete, and up-to-
date as is deemed necessary for the purposes for which it is to be used.
We will make sure to keep your Personal Information sufficiently accurate, complete, and
up-to-date, to minimize the possibility that inappropriate information may be used to make
a decision about you.
If Aviva has any doubt about your Personal Information being accurate, complete and/or
up-to-date, given that there is a business need, you may be contacted to verify the
information currently available, and amendments shall be made where necessary.
If we are unable to verify your Personal Information or contact you, we may be limited in
our ability to service your insurance needs.
PRINCIPLE SEVEN: Safeguards
Aviva shall protect Personal Information by establishing and operating security
safeguards appropriate to the sensitivity of the information, which is held, and to
prevent any unauthorized activity relative to the information.
Responsibility for safeguarding:
                                                                                         10

Aviva is responsible for safeguarding your Personal Information from loss, theft,
unauthorized access, disclosure, copying, use, or modification, regardless of the format in
which it is stored.
Methods of Safeguarding
The nature of the safeguards will vary depending on sensitivity, amount, distribution,
format and method of storage of the Personal Information. In general, the following are
observed:
       Personal Information is not left unattended out in the open;
       Access to Personal Information is only permitted when a legitimate business need
        exists;
       Personal Information is not photocopied, modified, disclosed, or destroyed without
        the specific consent and order of the responsible employee;
       When information is supplied to a third party, only necessary information is
        released from a sensitive file, rather than the complete file;
       No unescorted individual is given access to floors where sensitive information is
        retained;
       Passwords are changed on a periodic basis, and are not shared under any
        circumstances;
       Sensitive files are segregated and only authorized individuals allowed access;
       All mail received after hours is secured in the mail and supply area;
       Information of a sensitive nature is transferred to third parties by secure means;
        and
       Offsite information is stored in a secure location.
Aviva employees are required to be diligent about safeguarding Personal Information. We
take particular care with sensitive Personal Information such as:
       Medical/hospital records;
       Employment records;
       Income tax returns;
       Criminal records; and
       Financial records.
Information Received from Third Parties
Aviva employees adhere to the same diligence for Personal Information received from
outside Aviva and adhere to any higher standard of third parties if so contracted.
Destruction of Information
All Personal Information that is no longer required for its original purpose and has been
retained for the minimum required term shall be destroyed, erased, made anonymous, or
archived to the secure limited access site.
                                                                                       11

PRINCIPLE EIGHT: Openness
Aviva shall make available to individuals upon receipt of a written request, specific
information about its policies and practices relating to the management of Personal
Information and its complaints handling process.
Upon request, Aviva will provide an explanation of its Policy with respect to the
management of Personal Information. You can contact our Privacy Officer with any
inquiries or complaints or if you require further information.
PRINCIPLE NINE: Customer Access
Aviva shall, upon the receipt of a written request from individuals, inform them of
the existence, use, and disclosure of any Personal Information about them, and they
shall be given access to such information except as may be limited by law. Aviva
shall amend Personal Information as deemed appropriate to ensure continued
accuracy.
Requests for disclosure must be made in writing, by fax, email, or letter. We respond to
all requests within 30 days.
It is important to verify that the individual requesting information is in fact the person in
question. For this reason we demand that all inquiries be in writing and that our responses,
also in writing are sent to the address we have on file. Any alternative handling will require
mandatory validation of the requestor’s identity and address information.
Aviva will assist any individual who needs help in preparing the request.
Any responses shall be provided in an understandable manner with adequate explanation
of abbreviations or codes. Upon request, Aviva will provide access to Personal Information
in an alternative format for individuals with sensory disabilities, if conversion to an alternate
format is reasonable and necessary.
Timeframe for Responding to the Request
Reponses shall be made within 30 days of receipt of the request. However, if an extension
is required, a notice of extension for up to an additional 30 days will be sent to you, within
30 days of receipt of the request, stating the reasons for the extension, the new time limit
and explaining your right to complain to the Privacy Commissioner of Canada, or if
applicable, the Provincial Privacy Commissioner about the extension.
Refusal of Request for Disclosure
If a request for disclosure is denied, we will provide an explanation. The individual will be
informed that he/she can challenge the denial of the request through Aviva's Privacy
Officer via the Complaints Handling Process [see Principle Ten: Challenging Compliance]
or the Federal or Provincial Privacy Commissioner.
Examples of acceptable reasons for non-disclosure include:
        Prohibitive cost
                                                                                              12

       Personal Information that contains information about other individuals that cannot
        be severed
       Legal and security litigation, or commercial proprietary reasons
       Disclosure could reasonably be expected to threaten the life or security of another
        individual
Amending Details
If you successfully demonstrate the inaccuracy or incompleteness of Personal Information,
Aviva will amend the information, as required (correction, deletion, addition). Where
appropriate, the amended information shall be transmitted to applicable third parties
having access to the information in question.
Maintenance of Records
All amendments resulting from this process are formally recorded with an explanation
given, if necessary.
When a challenge is not resolved to the satisfaction of the individual, Aviva shall record
the substance of the unresolved challenge. When appropriate, the existence of the
unresolved challenge shall be transmitted to third parties having access to the information
in question.
Personal Information that is the subject of a request or has been used to make a decision
about an individual shall be retained as long as is necessary to allow the individual to
exhaust any recourse that they may have under the applicable privacy legislation.
Cost of the Disclosure
We may charge you for providing access to your information but only after first advising
you of the approximate cost.
PRINCIPLE TEN: Challenging Compliance
Aviva shall provide a means for individuals to challenge compliance with the above
with Aviva’s Privacy Officer.
Recognizing and Recording a Complaint or Inquiry
If you feel at any time that we are not complying with the principles set out in our Privacy
Policy, you may contact our Privacy Officer in writing.
For an inquiry/complaint on privacy that is received via telephone: the Privacy Officer’s
address information is provided along with advice to the individual to put his/her
inquiry/complaint in writing to our Privacy Officer.
The Privacy Officer or designate receives all inquiries and complaints, coordinates
responses, ensures responses meet Privacy requirements, and ensures that responses
are timely.
                                                                                          13

Investigating
All Privacy complaints received are investigated. If we find a complaint is justified, Aviva
attempts to resolve it. If necessary, we modify our policies and procedures to ensure that
other individuals will not experience the same concerns.
The investigation will involve a review of the facts in order to understand your complaint
by:
       Referring to the individual file (information both in the database and on paper);
       Referencing the Privacy Policy;
       Discussion with staff member(s) who were dealing with the individual/file; and
       Any other sources or documentation that may provide relevant information.
Acknowledging and Responding
If the inquiry/complaint cannot be resolved immediately, we will advise you that your
inquiry/complaint is being reviewed and when you can expect an answer. If you have any
concerns about our policy or treatment of your Personal Information and we have not been
able to resolve it, you will be advised to contact the office of the Privacy Commissioner of
Canada, or if applicable, the Provincial Privacy Commissioner. Our Privacy Officer will
provide this contact information on request.
Follow up
The Privacy Officer or designate will, if warranted and appropriate, contact you to verify
whether or not the matter has been resolved satisfactorily.
If the solution means that Aviva needs to alter its practices and procedures then the
Privacy Officer or designate is responsible for ensuring such changes are made.
Monitoring of Privacy Complaint Handling Procedures
On a periodic basis, the Privacy Officer or designate will review the complaints process to
ensure a fair, appropriate, and prompt process is in place.
Updates to our Policy
Aviva is always considering opportunities to improve or update communication to its
customers, streamline its business, but at all times be compliant with the law. Our Privacy
Policy as a result, is not necessarily a static document. Aviva, therefore, reserves the right
to alter the Privacy Policy from time to time. Such changes will be effective 10 days
following the posting of the change on this web site. For the most up to date information,
please revisit this web site or contact our Privacy Officer.
Date policy posted: September 2016
                                                                                           14

                                    APPENDIX
How to Contact Aviva’s Privacy Officer
In writing:              Privacy Officer
                         Aviva Canada Inc.
                         10 Aviva Way
                         Suite 100
                         Markham, Ontario L6G 0G1
By Phone/Fax:            Tel: 1-800-387-4518 x54171
                         Fax: 416-755-4075
By Email:                CAPrivacyOfficer@aviva.com
The member companies of Aviva Canada Inc.,
include:
           Aviva General Insurance Company
           Aviva Insurance Company of Canada
           Aviva Warranty Services Inc.
           Bay-Mill Specialty Insurance Adjusters Inc.
           Elite Insurance Company
           Insurance Agent Service Inc.
           OIS Ontario Insurance Service Limited
           Pilot Insurance Company
           S&Y Insurance Company
           Scottish & York Insurance Co. Limited
           Services d'Assurance Youville Inc.
           Traders General Insurance Company
                                                        15
